<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Core v2 on CloudBees Technologists</title>
    <link>https://technologists.dev/tags/core-v2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Core v2 on CloudBees Technologists</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 09:05:15 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://technologists.dev/tags/core-v2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Securely Using Cloud Services from Jenkins Kubernetes Agents</title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/posts/best-practices-for-cloudbees-core-jenkins-on-kubernetes/securely-using-cloud-services-from-jenkins-kubernetes-agents/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 09:05:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/posts/best-practices-for-cloudbees-core-jenkins-on-kubernetes/securely-using-cloud-services-from-jenkins-kubernetes-agents/</guid>
      <description>In the second part of this series on best practices for Jenkins (and CloudBees Core) on Kubernetes we will continue to look at security. In this post we will look at how to reduce security risk of using cloud services from Jenkins Kubernetes agents, similar to how the previous post in this series showed how Kubernetes Pod Security Policies can be used with Jenkins Kubernetes agents to limit the security risk of Jenkins agent containers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Kubernetes Pod Security Policies with CloudBees Core - Jenkins</title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/posts/best-practices-for-cloudbees-core-jenkins-on-kubernetes/core-psp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2019 05:05:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/posts/best-practices-for-cloudbees-core-jenkins-on-kubernetes/core-psp/</guid>
      <description>What are Pod Security Policies? Although Kubernetes Pod Security Policies are still a beta feature of Kubernetes they are an important security feature that should not be overlooked. Pod Security Policies (PSPs) are built-in Kubernetes resources that allow you to enforce security related properties of every container in your cluster. If a container in a pod does not meet the criteria for an applicable PSP then it will not be scheduled to run.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>