<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CloudBees Technologists</title>
    <link>https://technologists.dev/authors/logan-donley/</link>
    <description>Recent content on CloudBees Technologists</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://technologists.dev/authors/logan-donley/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Amazon ECS vs EKS for running CloudBees Core/Jenkins</title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/posts/eks-vs-ecs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 05:05:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/posts/eks-vs-ecs/</guid>
      <description>A question my colleagues and I are often asked is &amp;ldquo;if I&amp;rsquo;m already using ECS is there any point in moving to EKS (or Kubernetes in general) for running CloudBees Core?&amp;rdquo; Both Amazon ECS and EKS are great products, but we have a strong preference towards Kubernetes. We&amp;rsquo;ll take a look at why in this post.
What are ECS and EKS? These are both services from AWS which deal with container orchestration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serverless Preview Environments and GitOps with CloudBees Core and Google Cloud Run</title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/posts/cloud-run-with-core/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 05:05:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/posts/cloud-run-with-core/</guid>
      <description>Google Cloud Run is Google Cloud&amp;rsquo;s serverless platform for stateless containerized applications that leverage HTTP and event driven workloads. Cloud Run can be fully managed or you can use Cloud Run for Anthos to deploy applications in an Anthos GKE cluster running on Google Cloud or on-premises.
CloudBees Core is an enterprise version of Jenkins that provides better scalability, manageability, security and availability by running on and leveraging Kubernetes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to GitOps - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/posts/gitops-series-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/posts/gitops-series-part-1/</guid>
      <description>GitOps is a concept that was first coined by Weaveworks in their GitOps - Operations by Pull Request post. The idea itself wasn&amp;rsquo;t anything particularly new, people had been doing automated operations with infrastructure-as-code for years. But now that there was a descriptive new name for this concept, the DevOps community has really started to embrace it. Especially with the ever growing prevalence of Kubernetes.
If you haven&amp;rsquo;t already done so, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend reading that Weaveworks post since it is always good to understand the origination of a concept.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>