<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>kubernetes on CloudBees Technologists</title>
    <link>https://cb-technologists.github.io/tags/kubernetes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in kubernetes on CloudBees Technologists</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 10:50:46 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cb-technologists.github.io/tags/kubernetes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Technologists Lightning Talks for DevOps World | Jenkins World 2019 San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://cb-technologists.github.io/posts/lightning-talks-dw-jw-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 10:50:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cb-technologists.github.io/posts/lightning-talks-dw-jw-2019/</guid>
      <description>The Technologists will be giving a bunch of lightning talks in the DevOps Theater at this years DevOps World | Jenkins World in San Francisco. Some of the topics we will be covering include (many of which we have already blogged about):
 Self-Updating Jenkins: GitOps for Jenkins Configuration  This Lightning Talk will explore using GitOps to automate config updates for the CloudBees Jenkins Distribution.  Jenkins Plugin Management as Code  Let’s admit it, Jenkins Plugin management can be a pain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to GitOps - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://cb-technologists.github.io/posts/gitops-series-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cb-technologists.github.io/posts/gitops-series-part-1/</guid>
      <description>GitOps is a concept that was first coined by Weaveworks in their GitOps - Operations by Pull Request post. The idea itself wasn&amp;rsquo;t anything particularly new, people had been doing automated operations with infrastructure-as-code for years. But now that there was a descriptive new name for this concept, the DevOps community has really started to embrace it. Especially with the ever growing prevalence of Kubernetes.
If you haven&amp;rsquo;t already done so, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend reading that Weaveworks post since it is always good to understand the origination of a concept.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Updating Jenkins: GitOps for Jenkins Configuration</title>
      <link>https://cb-technologists.github.io/posts/cjd-casc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 17:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cb-technologists.github.io/posts/cjd-casc/</guid>
      <description>In this blog post, we&amp;rsquo;ll walk through creating a self-updating instance of the CloudBees Jenkins Distribution, with all configuration stored as code in a GitHub repository.
We&amp;rsquo;ll deploy the CJD master as a StatefulSet in a Kubernetes cluster, configure the master using the Jenkins Configuration as Code plugin, and set up a TLS certificate through cert-manager. Finally, we&amp;rsquo;ll seed a Pipeline job that updates the master upon commit to the Git repository that contains the configuration - enabling GitOps for Jenkins itself.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>