<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors on CloudBees Technologists</title>
    <link>https://technologists.dev/authors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Authors on CloudBees Technologists</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://technologists.dev/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/authors/david-ca%C3%B1adillas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 01:51:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/authors/david-ca%C3%B1adillas/</guid>
      <description>David Cañadillas is a tech passionate Senior Solutions Architect at CloudBees. He is an Industrial Engineer who loves software technologies, so he found the perfect mix of both worlds: DevOps. David has been more than 10 years helping organisations to translate software technical solutions into business from presales and technical consulting roles. When David is not playing around with Jenkins, Kubernetes and CI/CD pipelines, he is probably riding his Harley or enjoying the family.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/authors/casey-vega/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/authors/casey-vega/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/authors/josh-hendrick/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/authors/josh-hendrick/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/authors/kurt-madel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/authors/kurt-madel/</guid>
      <description>Kurt Madel is Director, Global Solution Architecture for CloudBees and works out of their office in Richmond, VA. He has over 20 years of software engineering and architecture experience, including DevOps in real world scenarios. He and his team work with CloudBees customers, and internally with CloudBees product, sales, and engineering teams, to help customers learn and use the CloudBees continuous delivery platform architected for the enterprise. Prior to joining CloudBees he was a software engineer at Capital One where he developed APIs for Apple Pay and helped lead their REST API initiative to include leading the development of a micro-service framework used by thousands of developers and streamlining of CI / CD processes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/authors/logan-donley/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/authors/logan-donley/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/authors/matt-elgin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/authors/matt-elgin/</guid>
      <description>Matt Elgin is a Solutions Architect at CloudBees based out of Richmond, Virginia. Previously delivering software projects as a technology consultant, he now leverages his passion for all things automation to help organizations of all sizes achieve their DevOps goals.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>