<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>jenkins on CloudBees Technologists</title>
    <link>https://cb-technologists.github.io/tags/jenkins/</link>
    <description>Recent content in jenkins on CloudBees Technologists</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 05:50:46 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cb-technologists.github.io/tags/jenkins/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Jenkins Plugins: The Good, the Bad and the Ugly</title>
      <link>https://cb-technologists.github.io/posts/jenkins-plugins-good-bad-ugly/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 05:50:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cb-technologists.github.io/posts/jenkins-plugins-good-bad-ugly/</guid>
      <description>There are over 1400 Jenkins plugins and that is both a blessing and a curse. Of those 1400 plugins only a small percentage are well maintained and tested, and even fewer (140 of 1400+) are part of the CloudBees Assurance Program (CAP) as verified and/or compatible plugins - well tested to interoperate with the rest of the CAP plugins (and their dependencies) and with a specific LTS version of Jenkins.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extending Jenkins X for Traditional Deployments with CloudBees Flow</title>
      <link>https://cb-technologists.github.io/posts/jenkins-x-flow-integration/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 12:47:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cb-technologists.github.io/posts/jenkins-x-flow-integration/</guid>
      <description>Jenkins X is quickly becoming the de facto standard for high performing teams wanting to do CI/CD in a highly scalable and fault tolerant environment. For those who haven’t gotten the opportunity to try out Jenkins X, it allows teams to run CI/CD workloads natively in a Kubernetes environment while taking advantage of modern operating patterns like GitOps and serverless architectures. For teams wanting to modernize their continuous integration and continuous deployment capabilities, Jenkins X is the go to solution.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>