<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cert-manager on CloudBees Technologists</title>
    <link>https://technologists.dev/tags/cert-manager/</link>
    <description>Recent content in cert-manager on CloudBees Technologists</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 15:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://technologists.dev/tags/cert-manager/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to GitOps - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/posts/gitops-series-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/posts/gitops-series-part-1/</guid>
      <description>GitOps is a concept that was first coined by Weaveworks in their GitOps - Operations by Pull Request post. The idea itself wasn&amp;rsquo;t anything particularly new, people had been doing automated operations with infrastructure-as-code for years. But now that there was a descriptive new name for this concept, the DevOps community has really started to embrace it. Especially with the ever growing prevalence of Kubernetes.
If you haven&amp;rsquo;t already done so, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend reading that Weaveworks post since it is always good to understand the origination of a concept.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Updating Jenkins: GitOps for Jenkins Configuration</title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/posts/cjd-casc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 17:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/posts/cjd-casc/</guid>
      <description>In this blog post, we&amp;rsquo;ll walk through creating a self-updating instance of the CloudBees Jenkins Distribution, with all configuration stored as code in a GitHub repository.
We&amp;rsquo;ll deploy the CJD master as a StatefulSet in a Kubernetes cluster, configure the master using the Jenkins Configuration as Code plugin, and set up a TLS certificate through cert-manager. Finally, we&amp;rsquo;ll seed a Pipeline job that updates the master upon commit to the Git repository that contains the configuration - enabling GitOps for Jenkins itself.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>