<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>devsecops on CloudBees Technologists</title>
    <link>https://technologists.dev/tags/devsecops/</link>
    <description>Recent content in devsecops on CloudBees Technologists</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 07:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://technologists.dev/tags/devsecops/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Safety First with Jenkins and Snyk</title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/posts/jenkins-snyk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/posts/jenkins-snyk/</guid>
      <description>Implementing security scanning as a preventative measure in your CI pipeline. Overview Today’s developers are being empowered to expeditiously innovate, creating new software capabilities and building continuous customer value. At CloudBees, we commonly tell our customers:
 &amp;ldquo;Every business is a software business and is under pressure to innovate constantly. This increased velocity introduces new business risks. CloudBees is building the world&amp;rsquo;s first end-to-end automated software delivery system (SDM), enabling companies to balance governance and developer freedom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CloudBees&#39; Cross Team Collaboration for Asynchronous DevSecOps</title>
      <link>https://technologists.dev/posts/cloudbees-cross-team-and-dev-sec-ops/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 07:50:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://technologists.dev/posts/cloudbees-cross-team-and-dev-sec-ops/</guid>
      <description>What is Cross Team Collaboration? CloudBees&amp;rsquo; Cross Team Collaboration provides the ability to publish an event from a Jenkins job that triggers any other Jenkins job on the same master or different masters that are listening for that event. It is basically a light-weight PubSub for CloudBees Core Masters connected to CloudBees Operations Center. Jenkins has had the ability to trigger other jobs for quite a while now (and with CloudBees this is even easy to do across Masters), but it always required that the upstream job be aware of the downstream job(s) to be triggered.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>